<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">

    <properties>
        <title>IDS Java Client User Manual</title>
    </properties>

    <body>

        <section name="Introduction">


            <p>The IDS APIs provides easy access from Java and Python to a deployed ICAT Data Service (IDS)
                Files may be uploaded, downloaded and
                deleted from the
                IDS. When a file is uploaded or deleted the action is recorded in ICAT as a new or deleted
                Datafile. ICAT authorization
                rules are used
                to assign the same rights to access the data as those granted to the metadata.
            </p>

            <p>
                Installation and accessing from maven is explained in
                <a href="installation.html">Client Installation.</a>
            </p>

            <subsection name="Setting Up">
                <p>Create an IDSClient instance passing it the URL of the machine providing the service. Irrespective of language, &lt;hostname&gt;
                    as
                    used in the code snippets below should be the full name of the IDS server. For a secure installation, just specifying
                    localhost
                    will not work, the name must match what is on the host certificate.
                </p>

                <h4>From Java</h4>

                <code>
                    URL url = new URL("https://&lt;hostname&gt;:8181")
                    <br />
                    client = new IdsClient(url);
                </code>

                <h4>From Python</h4>

                <code>
                    import ids
                    <br />
                    <br />
                    url = "https://&lt;hostname&gt;:8181"
                    <br />
                    client = ids.IdsClient(url)
                </code>

            </subsection>

            <subsection name="Using it">
                <p>Most calls to the IDS require an ICAT sessionId so first log in to ICAT to get a sessionId.</p>

                <p>
                    Please consult the
                    <a href="apidocs">javadoc</a>
                    for a full explanation of what all the calls do for Java. The python documentation is available in the usual way. Just enter
                    <code>pydoc ids</code>
                    from the command line.
                </p>

                <p>It should be noted that the Java and Python apis are different in style. The python has retained the Java style method names but
                    getData has been split into two calls: getData and getPreparedData. The DataSelection object in the Java calls is replaced by
                    optional named lists of ids.
                </p>


            </subsection>



        </section>
    </body>

</document>
